Guide to the Andrew St. George Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Andrew St. George papers
1957-1990
MS 1912
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
30.25
(45 boxes)
Photographs, films, slides, writings, and clippings, documenting Andrew St. George's career as a photojournalist in numerous regions, including the Caribbean and Latin America.
St. George, Andrew, 1924-2001
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Jean Szentgyorgyi by the Latin American Curator, June 2009; transferred from Latin American Curator, 2012.
Associated Materials
Cuban Revolution Collection, MS 650. Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Conditions Governing Access
NOTE: This collection will be closed to researchers for processing from May 2019 until August 2019.
Boxes 7-10 and 42-43 of Accession 2010-M-036 and Accession 2013-M-020 are open for research.
Boxes 1-6 and 11-41 of Accession 2010-M-036 require permission to access from the Latin American Collection Curator, Yale University Library.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
Andrew St. George was born in Hungary in 1923. He attended Columbia University in the 1950s but never graduated, preferring to find work as a writer and photojournalist in order to support his wife and frequent collaborator, Jean, and their growing family. St. George worked for United States military intelligence in Vienna after World War II. For the rest of his life he worked as an investigative reporter and photographer, especially focusing on Latin America. His interest in that region began when he conducted one of the first full-length interviews with Fidel Castro and members of his guerrilla army in the Sierra Maestra during the fall of 1957. The interview was later published in Look magazine. St. George also published accounts of his time with the guerrillas in Coronet, Cavalier, and Life. During 1959 and most of 1960, St. George lived in Cuba; by the summer of 1960, he had become disillusioned with the Cuban Revolution's authoritarianism. During the next three decades he pursued his career as a photojournalist, including working a number of years at Spotlight Magazine in Washington, D.C. He had two sons, Andrew and Tom. St. George died on May 2, 2001.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of photographs, films, slides, writings, and clippings, documenting Andrew St. George's career as a photojournalist in numerous regions, including the Caribbean and Latin America.
Cuba -- History -- Revolution, 1959; Cuba -- Politics and government; Cuba -- Social conditions; Havana (Cuba); Sierra Maestra (Cuba: Mountains); Castro, Raúl, 1930-; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016; Guevara, Che, 1928-1967; St. George, Andrew, 1924-2001
- Original inventory, Accession 2010-M-036
  - Photographs
    - General (Box 1, Box 1A)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Permission to access material is required from the Latin American Curator, Yale University.
    - General (Box 2)
    - General (Box 3)
    - General (Box 4)
    - General (Box 5)
    - General (Box 6)
    - Cuba
      - 26th of July guerrillas, Fidel's Column, Sierra Maestra, Circa 1958 (Box 7, Folder 1)
        Scope and Contents
        The images of guerrillas in Fidel Castro's column are engaged in wartime activities and scenes of everyday life. The photographs show the preparation of hand-made bombs in a clandestine bomb shop run by a bearded veteran of the Spanish Civil War; guerrillas manning a look-out post from the mountains near El Cobre, Oriente while others are engaged in routine activities such as cleaning a rifle, repairing a uniform with a Singer sewing machine, relaxing with children in the guerrilla camp, enjoying a pig roast, and a man applying talcum powder to a young boy.
      - Portraits of guerrillas and guerrilla-affiliated family members in Fidel's column, 1957 June and Nov, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        There are portraits of individual guerrillas including Fidel Castro, Felipe Guerra Matos (in 1957 and January 1959), as well as the later infamous Manuel Piñeiro, better known as Barba Roja. Piñeiro was chief of Cuba's domestic intelligence service, commonly known as G2, during the 1960s and later a top official in the Sovietized Ministry of the Interior after 1968. There is a composite and retouched photograph with founders of the first 26th of July guerrilla column in the Sierra Maestra, probably from June 1957. Included in this photograph are an unknown rebel, Che Guevara (second from left), Universo Sanchez (third from left), Raul Castro (fourth from the left), followed by Fidel Castro (on Raul's left), Crescencio Perez, and Andrew St. George on the far right with his hand on his left hip. The third man on the right on his haunches is Juan Almeida Bosque. A cropped version of this photograph is in Box 8, folder 2. One picture shows Fidel with a young couple at his side and bearded guerrillas. The woman is wearing a fashionable scarf in her hair and full make-up while the man is relatively well-shaven. On the back of this image, St. George includes a caption that says "Pura Pradier, a young Habana musician and concert singer (center) was often seen with Castro after rebel victory. Here she is shown with him on mountain maneuvers." There are individual images of Fidel and other unidentified guerrillas, including a young woman inspecting a hand gun and a black Cuban with glasses posing with a rifle.
      - Guerrillas, field medicine, school children, 1958 October - December (Box 7, Folder 3)
        These images document the rebel forces' policy of taxing the owners of local coffee estates in Oriente on the production and processing of each 100-pound bag of coffee. In one photograph Manuel Boronato, a blonde rebel officer, is shown overseeing the drying of beans, while in another a black officer and a group of armed female guerrillas appear to be involved in the weighing and taxing of each bag. Also included are photographs of a field hospital for treating local peasants and wounded rebels as well as a school for peasant children in a zone liberated by the forces of Raúl Castro in the summer of 1958. Most images were taken between October and December 1958 on St. George's last trip to Cuba before the triumph of the Revolution in January 1959.
      - Guerrillas engaged in requisitioning of vehicles, levying "tolls," temporary take-overs of small villages and company stores, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        There are images of guerrillas from Raúl Castro's column requisitioning vehicles and stopping cars on the highway for the payment of "tolls" in 1958. Also included are images of the temporary takeover of a small village called Matías by guerrillas under the command of blond officer Manuel Boronato. The guerrillas are shown at a small company store, enjoying (for the first time) a juke box, as well as local nighttime activities, such as a vigil held in honor of the Virgin of Charity, with peasants of the region. There is one print of a group of armed rebels listening to a woman playing the piano that was taken in the first week of January 1959 according to note on the back of the print. There is also one print of Batista's helmeted forces appearing to attack a rebel hideout.
      - Rebel army takes control of military and police stations in Oriente; Fidel's 1st speech in Santiago, Oriente, Circa 1959 (Box 7, Folder 5)
        Included among these images are guerrillas taking over major military installations, munitions sites, and police stations on January 1, 1959. One of the stations was the police headquarters at Guántanamo where a rebel and a former Batistiano soldier can be seen guarding the entrance together. Castro is seen giving his first speech to the nation from the main plaza at Santiago de Cuba, with Crescenio Pérez at his side and several uniformed Batistiano police standing around him. Two related images show the crowd listening to the speech. There are also two prints of Catholic priests who served in the 26th of July underground: one is Francisco Guzmán who is seen wearing white robe and cross while the other is an unidentified priest, probably a Franciscan. There are several prints of the liberation of a prison where political prisoners were housed in terrible conditions. There is also a print, taken in Havana most likely, of rebel officer Colonel Darío Rubén de los Santos sharing a happy moment with the Batista officials who appear to be manning a military prison (St. George writes on the back "inside the fortress").
      - Raúl Castro, 1st days of January 1959, 1959 January (Box 7, Folder 6)
        The images in this folder focus on Raúl Castro. In an up-close photograph, he is smiling for the camera while apparently giving a press conference in the early days of January 1959. On the wall behind him appears a list of radio stations broadcasting the press conference: CMKC Radio Oriente / CNC Circuito Nacional / CMBC Radio Progreso / CMCF Unión Radio / CMK? (obscured by RC's head) Red Provincial / C???? Radio Min (also obscured). He is also shown in his first meeting with his fiancée, Vilma Espín, on January 1, 1959, after many months of separation. One photograph is of an airplane cabin with Raúl Castro and gunmen stationed near the door.
      - First week of January 1959: Fidel's victory caravan to Havana; speeches and press conference along the way; civilian leaders of 26th of July Movement, 1959 January (Box 7, Folder 7)
        All photographs in this folder date from the first week of January 1959. Included are images of Fidel Castro's caravan of cars and requisitioned tanks making their way westward from Oriente to Havana. In several images Fidel Castro is shown chatting with nuns as he makes one of his famous impromptu stops along the way. One photograph includes Castro with several Americans: Dr. Judson U. McGuire, Jr. (on Castro's right), an entomologist with the United States Department of Agriculture; Jules Dubois (wearing black necktie) of the "Chicago Tribune", and McGuire's daughter wearing a white blouse. There are also two shots of the airplane that took civilian members of the new government to Havana. One shows Armando Hart, Haydée Santamaría (his wife), Luis Busch, secretary to President Manuel Urrutia, and José Llanuga, identified as "organ director in the U.S.". Another image of revolutionaries from the military and civilian wings of the 26th of July movement meeting on the tarmac with a uniformed man described as Major Julio Martínez Paez, a medical doctor (St. George notes on the verso "Min of Health 1st fulltime doc, Havana surgeon"). There is a photograph of a young 18-year-old guerrilla drinking Coca Cola as he guards the entrance to a plane. St. George identifies this man as Hanibal Hidalgo "son of Mario". St. George also notes that the young man is doing guard duty as both Fidel Castro and the newly installed President Manuel Urrutia are on the plane. Two photographs taken at a Presidential Palace cocktail party in Havana show a rebel with Afro-style hair. On the back of one of these prints, St. George wrote, "At left one of Che Guevara aides allegedly killed with him in Bolivia." There is a print of the revolutionary cabinet and Fidel Castro; he still did not occupy a position in the new government at the first major news conference held in Havana. Fidel is seen standing at the microphones, speaking. There are two prints of homemade busts of Fidel Castro with lottery tickets that were sold on the street by a vendor. The verso of this photographs reads: "'22) Cuba's Castro Craze produces these plaster of Paris busts which are sold by vendors along with national lottery tickets throughout Cuba. July 6th, the 8th anniversary of his civil war, is being celebrated by the presence of the Communist cosmonaut Major Yuri Gagarin. Credit: Andrew St. George ©1961 Magnum Photos."
      - Plaza of the Presidential Palace, million-person rally to support the Revolutionary government's trial and executions of Batistianos, and trial in sports stadium of José Sosa Blanco, 1959 January (Box 7, Folder 8)
        This folder includes images of "Operation Truth," a campaign on the part of the revolutionary government to show American critics that the Cuban people supported the trial and execution of all intelligence and security forces of the Batista dictatorship that was responsible for committing atrocities against its opponents. A highlight of the campaign was the trial of Captain Jesús Sosa Blanco, commander of the military garrison in Holguín, Oriente Province, and one of the most despised batistiano officials on the island in Havana's National Stadium; the trial occurred on January 14, 1959, before 18,000 spectators and members of the international press corps. There are images in the folder showing a million-plus rally in support of revolutionary justice held before the Presidential Palace. There is a portrait of Elena Escardo, under arrest in Santiago de Cuba. The verso of this portrait describes her as a "Mexican actress, torrid romantic interest of Masferrer in the late Fifties; here shown under arrest in Santiago after Masferrer fled and Castro took over. She was shot as a suspected spy." There is another photograph showing two rebels standing before a large mound of earth. The caption reads: "WIDE WORLD PHOTOS. MASS GRAVE OF EXECUTED. SANTIAGO, CUBA.... This mound of earth covers the mass grave of 71 Batista followers reported executed yesterday by Cuban rebels. Rebel officers say four of those executed were found guilty of crimes at a Sunday night military tribunal. Rebel Capt. Frank Fiorino, (left) an American from Norfolk, Va., is one of the two men standing by the grave. January 13, 1959."
      - St. George's story on 1960 Carnival and tourist season in Havana, 1960 January-February (Box 7, Folder 9)
        These images were taken in January and February 1960 when Andrew St. George visited Cuba to write a story on the waning tourist industry. He also attended Havana's famous carnival that is documented in these photographs. The caption on one photograph reads: "Our best Masferrer picture, shot in 1958, when Masferrer was part owner of the casino in Havana's Hotel Riviera, shown here." A later caption on the same photograph reads: "This is old picture but historically interesting. Caption should make clear that Habana Libre Casino was closed by Castro some years ago."
      - Enma Castro's wedding at the National Cathedral (Havana), 1959 April (Box 7, Folder 10)
      - Fidel Castro meets with U. S. Ambassador Philip Bonsal in Cojímar, Cuba, 1959 March 6 (Box 7, Folder 11)
        Fidel Castro and U.S. Ambassador Philip W. Bonsal had their first face-to-face meeting on March 6, 1959, at Castro's villa in Cojímar. These photographs document that event. In one image an unidentified rebel officer is standing between Bonsal and Castro. Included are a number of pictures of Bonsal conversing with the Cuban Minister of Foreign Relations, Roberto Agramonte, possibly before Fidel arrived. There are photographs of others shown waiting and mingling in the same location.
      - Havana, Presidential Palace, U. S. Ambassador Philip Bonsal's presentation of diplomatic credentials to Cuban President Manuel Urrutia, 1959 March 5 (Box 7, Folder 12)
        These photographs document U.S. Ambassador Philip W. Bonsal presenting his diplomatic credentials in a formal ceremony to Cuban President Manuel Urrutia and his revolutionary cabinet.
      - U. S. Ambassador Philip Bonsal addressing ASTA convention, 1959 October 2 (Box 7, Folder 13)
        The photographs document U.S. Ambassador Philip W. Bonsal addressing a convention of the American Society of Travel Agents (ASTA) delegates in Habana's Blanquita Theatre on October 21, 1959. The convention was sponsored entirely by the revolutionary government that hoped to ignite Americans' interest in traveling to Cuba. The revolutionary government also wanted to thwart U.S. press and governmental caricatured depictions of the Revolution as "Communist," a charge consistently levied since January 1959 in an effort to discredit all changes in Cuba that would negatively impact U.S. business interests.
      - U. S. Ambassador Philip Bonsal and wife, arrival in Havana, Cuba, at the airport, 1959 February (Box 7, Folder 14)
        In February 1959 U.S. Ambassador Philip W. Bonsal and his wife arrived in Havana to take control of the U.S. mission.
      - U. S. Ambassador Philip Bonsal, press conference at U. S. Embassy on arrest of Comandante Huber-Matos, 1959 October (Box 7, Folder 15)
        In this photograph, U.S. Ambassador Philip W. Bonsal is holding a press conference in his office at the U.S. Embassy in Havana in October 1959. The occasion of this press conference was the crisis provoked by the arrest of revolutionary Commander Huber Matos and the simultaneous disappearance of Commander Camilo Cienfuegos.
      - U. S. Ambassador Philip Bonsal, wife, and DIER escort at Havana airfield, 1960? (Box 7, Folder 16)
        U.S. Ambassador Philip W. Bonsal and his wife are on the airport tarmac in the company of Departamento de Inteligencia del Ejercito Rebelde (D.I.E.R.) officials who were Cuba's top intelligence agents. D.I.E.R. was later named G2.
      - Mass rally, January 1959, former Spanish Socialist (Loyalist) Colonel Alberto Bayo, trainer of 26th of July guerrillas in Mexico before 1956 landing, 1959 January (Box 7, Folder 17)
        This is a photograph of Col. Alberto Bayo, a veteran of the Spanish Civil War. The caption on the verso reads: "The man who initiated Che Guevara into guerrilla warfare, former Spanish (Loyalist) Colonel Alberto Bayo (beard, civilian clothes) is shown here in Havana. Bayo trained Che in Mexico in 1956, went to prison briefly for his pains, then became important figure in new Cuba."
      - Fidel Castro's visit to Venezuela, 1959 January (Box 7, Folder 18)
        These photographs show Fidel Castro and his entourage during their January 1959 visit to Venezuela where they helped celebrate the anniversary of the fall of the Venezuelan dictatorship and President Romulo Betancourt's rise to power.
      - Hemingway's fishing tournament, 1959 May (Box 7, Folder 19)
        These photographs focus on Ernest Hemingway with Fidel Castro at Hemingway's May 1959 fishing tournament. The images include two shots of Mary and Ernest Hemingway in profile as they watch the boats returning with their catches. In one photograph, Castro is pictured holding all the top trophies for having caught the biggest fish. Similar and identical ones are also in Box 8, folder 22.
      - Trial of CIA agents who attempted to foment a counter-revolutionary guerrilla movement in Pinar del Río, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 20)
        These photographs are of the Revolutionary Tribunal trial of Austin Frank Young and Peter John Lambton. Young and Lambton were two former World War II American fighter pilots who organized a counterrevolutionary guerrilla force, apparently under the cover of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA), for the purpose of toppling the Castro-led government in September 1959. Their organization's name was The Cuban Democratic Legión. It counted on the support of such former Batista military officers in the Pinar del Río region as Juan Cruz Padrón and his brothers. Local peasants in the region were responsible for reporting these subversive activities to regional authorities, who promptly arrested Young, Lambton, and eight guerrilla recruits. At the trial, Young and Lambton were found guilty of conspiring under the cover of the CIA to topple the Cuban revolutionary government and sentenced to thirty years in prison. They were later released into United States custody following negotiations over the failed CIA-directed Bay of Pigs invasion in 1961. Other Cuban conspirators received sentences of between 3 and 25 years.
      - St. George's documentation of visiting delegation and advisors from "Red China", 1960 December (Box 8, Folder 1)
        These photographs document the presence of Chinese advisors, official journalists, and young volunteers in Cuba by December 1960. One photograph, taken in the Barrio Chino of Centro Habana, shows a small shop typical of that area of the city, selling canned food, dried fish, soap, packaged herbs, and other dry goods. The shop is attended by a middle-aged Chinese Cuban and patronized, in this picture, by a member of the Chinese delegation visiting Havana. Another photograph shows a slim Chinese Cuban in a business suit standing before a taxi and the recently opened Chinese government's solidarity center, still located in the same place, near Calle Zanja in Centro Habana. Four photographs show business-suited members of the Chinese delegation standing in front of a columned building in Havana, probably near El Prado or on El Prado. Another photograph shows Chinese visitors dressed as milicianos in white shirts, with several wearing hats, as they wave to a crowd at the main entrance to the Presidential Palace. The Chinese are leaving the Palace, ostensibly after meeting with President Osvaldo Dorticós and others. Two photographs include captions on the back. One shows a Chinese woman standing with Cuban laborers and a member of the Cuban armed forces. Its caption reads: "EXCLUSIVE PHOTO FROM EUROPEAN Der. CUBA, TODAY: Living proof that Chinese Communists are firmly entrenched in Cuba, is shown here. These Red Chinese volunteers have been sent by that country to work side by side with Cubans, in the Oriente Province of the Sierra Maestra Mountains, in the construction of houses, schools, etc. Our photographer managed to take this exclusive picture under threat of arrest. [dated] 91660" Stamped December 25, 1960. Also marked "Foto No 3" and "Cuba Comunismo." The second captioned photograph shows photographers from the international and domestic press standing on the Malecón in the presence of armed members of the National Revolutionary Police. A parade is clearly taking place and Cubans are lining the street as a car in the parade drives by. The caption on the back reads: "(17) RED CHINESE NEWSMEN, like this Sinjua agency photographer shown covering a political rally in Havana, now fan out from Cuba to every Latin country in the hemisphere."
      - Sierra Maestra, 1957-1958 (Box 8, Folder 2)